Zachary Hafen-Saavedra

PhD, Astrophysical Data Analysis

z.hafen.saavedra@gmail.com || (303) 819-8840 || zhafen.github.io || Chicago, IL || 📢 🛅



Summary

Data scientist with ten years of experience earned as a Northwestern University and UC Irvine computational astrophysicist. Extensive history leading interdisciplinary collaborations and communicating complex concepts. Seeking positions in data science and data analysis, especially social-justice-focused positions.

Skills

Techniques: data analysis (cleaning, sparse, big data, exploratory, time-series), machine learning, natural language processing, frequentist/Bayesian statistics, code testing, nested/multiscale modeling Interpersonal skills: technical leadership and management, storytelling, mentoring Tools: Python (numpy, pandas, matplotlib, scikit-learn), SQL, TensorFlow, Unix, C/C++, git, nltk,

Experience

Temporary Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion Data Analyst

Northwestern University, Center for Interdisc. Explor. and Research in Astrophysics

June 2023 - Present Evanston, IL

- Analyzed cultural-climate survey data, grouping race, gender, and professional role to identify sociosystemic strengths and weaknesses
- Automated data extraction from unstructured PDF documents to increase analysis speed by >100×

McCue Prize Postdoctoral Fellow in Cosmology

University of California-Irvine, Department of Physics and Astronomy

July 2020 - June 2023 Irvine, CA

- Employed natural language processing to convert >200,000 scientific abstracts to quantitative data
- Trained an ensemble voting model to use abstract word content and paper metadata to predict citation count to within 3 citations per year for 75% of the validation set
- Performed complex filtering of >2 TB of remote data via the NASA astrophysics data system API
- Spearheaded an international team spanning eight institutions to validate Bayesian statistical models

National Science Foundation Graduate Fellow in K-12 Education

Northwestern University, Department of Physics and Astronomy

June 2014 - July 2020 Evanston, IL

- Introduced >100 students from underrepresented backgrounds to data science by leading one of Chicago's first high-school data-science education initiatives
- · Created quantitative visualizations, educational explanatory visualizations, and award-winning artistic visualizations to communicate core messages
- Processed tens of TB of >20-dimensional data using high-performance-computing resources, reducing to <100 GB of highly-interpretable data
- Collaborated with a multidisciplinary range of scientists to publish (to date) 36 papers, 7 as a lead author

Education

The Erdős Institute 2023 **Data Science Certificate** Irvine, CA **Northwestern University** 2020 PhD, MS, Physics and Astronomy Evanston, IL Specialization: Astrophysical Data Analysis

University of Northern Colorado

2014 BS, Mathematical Physics Greeley, CO